Guide to the Martin Edward Hellman Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Martin Edward Hellman papers
1971-2013
1976-1988
SC1176
Hellman, Martin E.
3 Linear feet (and 265 megabytes)
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use.
Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Biographical/Historical note
Martin Edward Hellman was born in New York, NY in October 1945. He received his B.E. from New York University in 1966, and his M.S. and Ph.D. from Stanford University in 1967 and 1969, all in Electrical Engineering.
Prof. Hellman was at IBM's Watson Research Center from 1968-1969 and an Assistant Professor of Electrical Engineering at MIT from 1969-1971. Returning to Stanford in 1971, he served on the regular faculty until becoming Professor Emeritus in 1996. He has authored over seventy technical papers, ten US patents and a number of foreign equivalents.
Hellman is best known for his invention, with Diffie and Merkle, of public key cryptography. In addition to many other uses, this technology forms the basis for secure transactions on the Internet. He has also been a long-time contributor to the computer security debate, starting with the issue of DES's key size in 1975, serving (1994-96) on the National Research Council's Committee to Study National Cryptographic Policy, and currently serving on Verified Voting's Board of Advisors.
Prof. Hellman also has a deep interest in the ethics of technological development. With Prof. Anatoly Gromyko of Moscow, he co-edited Breakthrough: Emerging New Thinking, a book published simultaneously in Russian and English in 1987 during the rapid change in Soviet-American relations. His current project in this area, Defusing the Nuclear Threat, has been endorsed by a number of prominent individuals including a former Director of the National Security Agency, Stanford's President Emeritus, and two Nobel Laureates.
Scope and Contents
The materials consist of research files, subject files, publications and correspondence documenting public key cryptography and the Beyond War project.
Access Terms
Diffie, Whitfield.; Merkle, Ralph Charles.; Cryptography--United States--History--20th century.; Data encryption (Computer science)--United States.; Data Encryption Standard.; Information theory.
Collection Contents
- Public key cryptography
  - DES (Data Encryption Standard) - Misc. Correspondence, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Science Magazines, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Newsweek magazine & Datamation magazine, 1976-2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - DES - PR, circa 1970s - 1990s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - DES - IBM, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - NBS - Originals, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - NBS, 1975 Jun - 1977 Jan (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - DES - Congress, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Meyer - NSA - IEEE, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - DES - Bell Telephone Labs, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - NIST - DES RVW, 1992 Dec (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Misc. Articles Re: Marty, circa 1970s - 1980s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Racal-Milgo Patent Q. & MIT, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Resume - Photos, 1999 Dec (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Resume, Biogr., & Pics, circa 1990s (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - RSA - Notes, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - RSA License - MIT, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - EE478 - Originals, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - An Evaluation of the Data Encryption Standard (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Results of an Intial Attempt to Cryptanalyze the NBS Data Encryption Standard, 1976 Nov (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Crypto Bibliography, 1980 Nov (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Factoring Schroeppel, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "On the Necessity of Cryptanalytic Exhaustive Search" - Hellman, Karnin, & Reyneri, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Patents - Crypto, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Merkle, Ralph C., 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Secure Communications Over Insecure Channels - R. Merkle (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - A Knapsack Method, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Public Key Encipher, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Merkle, Ralph C. - Logs Mod P, 1976 Jul (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - EE478 - Martin Hellman - Class Notes, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Reprints - Martin Hellman and Thomas Cover, 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - IEEE Communications Magazine, 2002 May (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Information Theorectic Approach to Cryptography, 1974 Apr (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Inman, Bob letter to Hellman, 1980 Nov 22 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    Note of context from Professor Hellman (2014 May 29):
    I visited Inman at NSA a few weeks before this broke in the summer of 1980.
    The affair broke for me when I got a call from Gina Kolata telling me that Len Adleman had gotten a call or letter from NSF telling him that they could not fund a research proposal because NSA maintained they had a monopoly on government funding of crypto research. I told Gina that I had just had a meeting with Inman and either I'd been lied to or there was a serious misunderstanding, with the latter being my guess. I called Inman and told him what Gina had told me. He responded that someone had gotten the message terribly garbled, that Adleman was supposed to have been told that NSA would like to fund his work, not that NSF could not. I offered to suggest that Gina call him, and he heartily agreed. Gina did call Inman, but the story she ran in Science magazine stuck to the original version. Later conversations with the grant maker at NSF (Weingarten I believe) led me to believe that Inman's intent was not conveyed by lower level individuals at NSA, who rather took the old, high handed approach. So, both Gina's story and Inman's unhappiness at being misunderstood (expressed in his letter) may be well grounded, even though at first they appear mutually exclusive.
    My arguments about a compulsory system not working, and NSA needing the good will of the academic researchers must have won out, because he assured me that a voluntary system would be used instead. And that, in general, NSA would take a less confrontational approach.
- Beyond War project, 1984-1988
  - Soviet Visit, 1988 Jan-Apr (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Beyond War International Scientific Initiative / Santa Barbara and San Luis Obispo Talk, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Russian/Eng XLTN Q's, 1987 Nov (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Breakthrough (in Russian), copyright 1988 (Box 1)
  - Breakthrough (in English), 1988 (Box 1)
  - Hungary & USSR Trip, 1984 Aug (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - USSR/ Hungary Trip, 1984 Nov (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Moscow Trip - IFSNTB Meeting, 1986 Jul 11-13 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Nuclear Weapons - Arms Race, circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Moscow Trip, 1986 May 27-29 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Japan Trip, 1975 Jul-Aug (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - USA/USSR Task Force to Build a World Beyond War, 1985 Sep 9 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Earth Scientists for the Preservation of the Planet & The Problem - Victor F. Weisskopf, 1986 May (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - USSR Trip - Notes, etc., 1985 Oct (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence b/w Richard Rathbun & Central Jersey Region Beyond War, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - USA/ USSR Task Force (photos enclosed), 1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - USSR Trip - Notes/RPT, 1986 Jun (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - USSR Trip, 1988 Aug (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Moscow News Newspaper (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Update - Auth & Ed., 1987 Jan 27 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Biogs., 1987 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Axelrod - Multi-lingual (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Barton J. Bernstein, circa 1960s - 1980s (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Alan Borning, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Kenneth E. Boulding, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Paul Bracken, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Admiral Eugene J. Carroll Jr., 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Stephen F. Cohen, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Randall Forsberg, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Jerome D. Frank, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Papers w/ Notes on Nuclear Weapons - multiple authors, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Martin E. Hellman, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Sergei P Kapitza/ Martin E. Hellman, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Lawrence Klein, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Einar Kringlen, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Steven Kull, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Boris Raushenbakh, 1987 Jan 22 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - John M. Richardson Jr., 1987 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Everett M. Rogers, 1983-1987 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Richard R. Roney, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Linn Sennott, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Theodore B. Taylor, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - William L. Ury, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - I. William Zartman, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - The Story, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Fairchild Auditorium Presentations (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Soivet Papers - Old & Repr./ Sample (problems) & Burlatsky Dial (Box 2, Folder 43)
- 2013 Nov 19
- Computer files
  - Publications, 1971-2012; 42 computer file(s) (PDF)
    PDFs of most of Hellman's published papers. The numbered entries correspond to the publications page on his website.
  - Breakthrough History, 1986 Feb; 5 computer file(s)
    Images of a telegram and a telex, with crops of those showing the most important parts.
    Notes from Martin Hellman:
    860205 telegram.tiff 860205 telegram.tiff is a February 5, 1986 telegram from Andrei Kokoshin and another Soviet (Oznobistchev) whom I don't remember. Andrei was one of Evgeny Velikhov's Deputies -- and Velikhov was a VP of the Soviet Academy of Sciences, and later Gorbachev's Science Advisor. When we tried to meet with Velikhov in the Fall of 1984, he had us meet with Kokoshin instead. Later Kokoshin was a high level official in the Russian Ministry of Defense. When we worked with him, he was at the Academy of Science's Institute on USA and Canada, often known as IUSA. The telegram refers to "OUR COMMON WORKING MEETING IN SPRING ... NOT EARLIER THAN APRIL" In fact, that meeting did not take place until April 1987 (see picture caption on page 268 of the book). That was probably just as well since Gorbachev was not able to lift censorship until the Fall of 1986, so the earlier meeting date would have been severely hampered. In contrast, by April 1987 we were able to have totally unfettered discussions with the Soviets, with no limitations. There was a real discontinuity in late 1986.
    That telegram also refers to their "HAVE NOT GOT TELEX." Earlier, we had to use telegrams at about $0.25 per word to communicate in both directions, but by February 1986, Beyond War had obtained a CP/M program which allowed us to use a personal computer as a telex machine at roughly 1/10 the cost per word of telegrams. While the Soviets could receive our telexes, they could not send and had to use telegrams still.
    860225 telex.tiff is our reply to that telegram. A few words in the second paragraph are hard to read so here they are, "We have begun work based on the Draft Memorandum of Understanding which we formulated ...".
  - Cryptography History, 38 computer file(s)
    _Autobiography FrameMaker folder has a ReadMe.txt which explains what's there. I mostly included it for Chapter 1, which details my meeting with John Schwartz concerning the Meyer letter.
    Crypto History/1976 1110 cryptanalysis of DES.pdf has a scan of what I've called "the Lexar Report," except this is the Stanford version which we had to wait a few months to release for the reasons mentioned in my verbal comments when you were here.
    Crypto History/1977 0707 Meyer letter folder has files related to Meyer's letter sent to the IEEE, including that letter.
    Crypto History/1978 0703 TIME article has the July 3, 1978 TIME article in both scanned and text versions The text version is in Pages, a Mac word processor.
    Crypto History/IBM folder has correspondence between me and IBM when I was trying to get IBM to help increase the key size of DES.
    Crypto History/Inman folder has Bob Inman's 1980 handwritten letter to me.
    Crypto History/NBS folder has several files related to my interactions with NBS over DES' key size.
    Crypto History/Science Magazine articles folder has several articles from Science magazine related to my work. I own no rights to those articles since I did not write them.
    Inman letter--Note of context from Professor Hellman (2014 May 29):
  - Merkle, Ralph C., 1974-; 17 computer file(s)
  - Autobiography, Chapter 1, 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    Chapter from uncompleted memoir describing Hellman's interaction with John Schwartz and what happened at the 1977 symposium. This relates to the Meyer file. It was written about 20 years ago in a now obsolete word processor, and was translated into Word.